<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
    <info>
        <name></name>
        <update version="0.0.1">
            <file name="atavist-demonic.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Zenoverlordian/swordmeow-atavist/main/atavist-demonic.xml" />
        </update>
    </info>
    
    <element name="Demonic Aspect" type="Archetype" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC">
        <supports>Atavistic Aspect</supports>
        <description>
            <p>In certain cultures, manipulation of one’s blood for magic can be seen as the influence of hellish forces, outright feared as being caused by a demon. They might be wrong or, occasionally, may be very right. Whether some shard of a demon’s soul awakens hemomancy within you, you’ve made a pact of power, an old fiendish blood god occupies a forgotten line of your family tree, or you’ve been cursed by a godless soul, you have a demonic aspect about you.</p>
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_SPELLS" />
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_FIENDISH_CONSTITUTION" />
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_DEMONS_PYRE" />
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_HELLFIRE_OF_THE_ABYSS" />
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_ARCHDEMONS_PYRE" />
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_AVATAR_OF_A_DEMON_PRINCE" />
        </description>
        <sheet display="false">
            <description>Whether some shard of a demon’s soul awakens hemomancy within you, you’ve made a pact of power, an old fiendish blood god occupies a forgotten line of your family tree, or you’ve been cursed by a godless soul, you have a demonic aspect about you.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_SPELLS" level="3" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_FIENDISH_CONSTITUTION" level="3" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_DEMONS_PYRE" level="3" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_HELLFIRE_OF_THE_ABYSS" level="6" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_ARCHDEMONS_PYRE" level="10" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_AVATAR_OF_A_DEMON_PRINCE" level="18" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Demonic Aspect Spells" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_SPELLS">
        <description>
            <p>You learn the following spells. They are always prepared for you.</p>
            <h5>DEMONIC ASPECT SPELLS</h5>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr><td>Spell Levels</td><td>Spells</td></tr>
                </thead>
                <tr><td>1st</td><td>chaos bolt</td></tr>
                <tr><td>2nd</td><td>darkness</td></tr>
                <tr><td>3rd</td><td>summon lesser demons</td></tr>
                <tr><td>4th</td><td>summon greater demon</td></tr>
                <tr><td>5th</td><td>immolation</td></tr>
                <tr><td>6th</td><td>eyebite</td></tr>
            </table>
        </description>
        <sheet display="false" />
        <rules>
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_CHAOS_BOLT" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DARKNESS" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_SUMMON_LESSER_DEMONS" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_SUMMON_GREATER_DEMON" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_IMMOLATION" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_EYEBITE" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Fiendish Constitution" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_FIENDISH_CONSTITUTION">
        <description>
            <p>At 3rd level, your body takes on characteristics of demons. You register as a demon for any features that detect or interact with demons. Additionally, you can’t be poisoned and have resistance to poison damage. Finally, you can speak, read, and write Abyssal.</p>
            <p class="indent">If you wish, your body can begin to reflect these changes within you. The smell of brimstone could lightly surround you, your hair could thicken and redden, and your eyes might blacken.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>You register as a demon for any features that detect or interact with demons. Additionally, you can’t be poisoned and have resistance to poison damage. If you wish, your body can begin to reflect these changes within you.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_ABYSSAL" />
            <grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_POISON" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Demon's Pyre" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_DEMONS_PYRE">
        <description>
            <p>At 3rd level, you can enter or exit a demon’s pyre as a bonus action, granting you greater demonic might. If you do, your eyes change to your choice of color and iris shape. While in the pyre, you can’t be frightened, and each creature other than you within 5 feet of you takes 1d4 fire damage when you enter the pyre and at the start of each of your turns. This increases to 2d4 at 6th level, 3d4 at 10th, and 4d4 at 18th.</p>
            <p class="indent">The demon’s pyre lasts for up to 1 minute. You can use this feature a number of times equal to half your Constitution modifier (rounded up) and regain all expended uses when you finish a short or long rest.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description level="3" usage="{{constitution:modifier:half:up}}/Short Rest">You can enter or exit a demon’s pyre as a bonus action, granting you greater demonic might. If you do, your eyes change to your choice of color and iris shape. While in the pyre, you can’t be frightened, and each creature other than you within 5 feet of you takes 1d4 fire damage when you enter the pyre and at the start of each of your turns. The demon’s pyre lasts for up to 1 minute.</description>
            <description level="6" usage="{{constitution:modifier:half:up}}/Short Rest">You can enter or exit a demon’s pyre as a bonus action, granting you greater demonic might. If you do, your eyes change to your choice of color and iris shape. While in the pyre, you can’t be frightened, and each creature other than you within 5 feet of you takes 2d4 fire damage when you enter the pyre and at the start of each of your turns. The demon’s pyre lasts for up to 1 minute.</description>
            <description level="10" usage="{{constitution:modifier:half:up}}/Short Rest">You can enter or exit a demon’s pyre as a bonus action, granting you greater demonic might. If you do, your eyes change to your choice of color and iris shape. While in the pyre, you can’t be frightened, and each creature other than you within 5 feet of you takes 3d4 fire damage when you enter the pyre and at the start of each of your turns. The demon’s pyre lasts for up to 1 minute.</description>
            <description level="18" usage="{{constitution:modifier:half:up}}/Short Rest">You can enter or exit a demon’s pyre as a bonus action, granting you greater demonic might. If you do, your eyes change to your choice of color and iris shape. While in the pyre, you can’t be frightened, and each creature other than you within 5 feet of you takes 4d4 fire damage when you enter the pyre and at the start of each of your turns. The demon’s pyre lasts for up to 1 minute.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Hellfire of the Abyss" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_HELLFIRE_OF_THE_ABYSS">
        <description>
            <p>At 6th level, when you rend while in a demon’s pyre, you can change the weapon damage dealt to fire damage. Additionally, any fire damage you deal ignores resistances, and you have resistance to fire damage.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>When you rend while in a demon’s pyre, you can change the weapon damage dealt to fire damage. Additionally, any fire damage you deal ignores resistances, and you have resistance to fire damage.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_FIRE" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Archdemon's Pyre" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_ARCHDEMONS_PYRE">
        <description>
            <p>At 10th level, when one or more creatures take fire damage from your demon’s pyre, you can expend one spell slot to deal additional fire damage to them. The extra damage is 2d4 for a 1st-level slot, plus 1d4 for each spell level higher than 1st, to a maximum of 5d4. A celestial or fiend creature takes an additional 2d4 damage.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>When one or more creatures take fire damage from your demon’s pyre, you can expend one spell slot to deal additional fire damage to them. The extra damage is 2d4 for a 1st-level slot, plus 1d4 for each spell level higher than 1st, to a maximum of 5d4. A celestial or fiend creature takes an additional 2d4 damage.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Avatar of a Demon Prince" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_DEMONIC_AVATAR_OF_A_DEMON_PRINCE">
        <description>
            <p>At 18th level, when you enter a demon’s pyre, you can also enter an avatar of a demon prince. If you do so, for the duration of the pyre, you gain the following benefits:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You become a Large fiend with wings and a flying speed of 60 feet.</li>
                <li>You have advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</li>
                <li>You can create a whip of hellfire as a bonus action or when you enter a demon’s pyre. The whip deals fire damage, has a d12 damage die, and disappears if it leaves or grasp or when your pyre ends.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent">Once you enter an avatar, you can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description usage="1/Long Rest">When you enter a demon’s pyre, you can also enter an avatar of a demon prince. If you do so, for the duration of the pyre, you gain the following benefits: You become a Large fiend with wings and a flying speed of 60 feet. You have advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects. You can create a whip of hellfire as a bonus action or when you enter a demon’s pyre. The whip deals fire damage, has a d12 damage die, and disappears if it leaves or grasp or when your pyre ends.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>
    
</elements>