<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
    
    <element name="Anomalous Aspect" type="Archetype" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS">
        <supports>Atavistic Aspect</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You are an anomaly: an eldritch abomination. Blood magic was the hint at a deeper, older, and alien piece that has become part of you. Likely, your robust physical body was a coveted host for eldritch forces, pairing a consciousness with your mighty vessel. Because of its influence, you pick up strange qualities, and can momentarily release the anomalies within you. You can also pick up weird quirks. You can roll or select on the table below.</p>
            <h5>Anomalous Quirk</h5>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr><td>d6</td><td>Quirk</td></tr>
                </thead>
                <tr><td>1</td><td>When you wake up, daydream, or lose focus, you hear indecipherable tongues from many voices all around.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>2</td><td>The stars occasionally seem as if they’re not in the right place. Perhaps not yet.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>3</td><td>You talk about the current gods as if they are children.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>4</td><td>You have a taste for humanoid brains.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>5</td><td>Occasionally, surreal, eldritch words pour from your mouth while you are mid conversation.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>6</td><td>You refer to yourself as ‘we’ and ‘us’ instead of ‘I’ and ‘me.’</td></tr>
            </table>
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_SPELLS" />
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_RELEASE_THE_ANOMALY" />
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_AWAKENED_MIND" />
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_GRASP_OF_THE_STARS" />
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_GREATER_ANOMALY" />
            <div element="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_TO_THE_OLD_ONES" />
        </description>
        <sheet display="false">
            <description>You are an anomaly: an eldritch abomination. Blood magic was the hint at a deeper, older, and alien piece that has become part of you.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_SPELLS" level="3" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_RELEASE_THE_ANOMALY" level="3" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_GRASP_OF_THE_STARS" level="3" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_CRUORWROUGHT_HEARTEATER" level="6" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_GREATER_ANOMALY" level="10" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_TO_THE_OLD_ONES" level="18" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Anomalous Aspect Spells" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_SPELLS">
        <description>
            <p>You learn the following spells. They are always prepared for you.</p>
            <h5>ANOMALOUS ASPECT SPELLS</h5>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr><td>Spell Levels</td><td>Spells</td></tr>
                </thead>
                <tr><td>1st</td><td>dissonant whispers</td></tr>
                <tr><td>2nd</td><td>detect thoughts</td></tr>
                <tr><td>3rd</td><td>clairvoyance</td></tr>
                <tr><td>4th</td><td>confusion</td></tr>
                <tr><td>5th</td><td>contact other plane</td></tr>
                <tr><td>6th</td><td>disintegrate</td></tr>
            </table>
        </description>
        <sheet display="false" />
        <rules>
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DISSONANT_WHISPERS" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DETECT_THOUGHTS" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CLAIRVOYANCE" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CONFUSION" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CONTACT_OTHER_PLANE" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DISINTEGRATE" spellcasting="Atavist" prepared="true" />
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Release the Anomaly" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_RELEASE_THE_ANOMALY">
        <description>
            <p>Beginning when you choose this aspect at 3rd level, you can release the eldritch influence within you. As an action, you can reveal the anomaly. Tentacles erupt from your body, your eyes reveal the infinite void, and the might of the old gods fills you. The anomaly stays revealed for 1 minute. While the anomaly is revealed you gain the following benefits:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You gain two tentacles that sprout from your body, and four at 10th level. As a bonus action, you can attempt to grapple a number of creatures equal to your tentacles within 15 feet of you. You can grapple a creature of one size bigger than you otherwise could by using two, and a creature of two sizes bigger than you could with four.</li>
                <li>As an action, you can squeeze creatures grappled by your tentacles. A grappled creature must make a Strength saving throw (against your spell save DC) or take 3d6 bludgeoning damage. You can rend to the damage of the squeezing tentacles, affecting all creatures grappled by them.</li>
                <li>You gain temporary hitpoints immediately and again at the start of each of your turns equal to your Intelligence modifier.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent">You have a number of uses of this feature equal to your Intelligence modifier, and regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description action="Action" usage="{{intelligence:modifier}}/Long Rest" level="3">As an action, you can reveal the anomaly. Tentacles erupt from your body, your eyes reveal the infinite void, and the might of the old gods fills you. The anomaly stays revealed for 1 minute. While the anomaly is revealed you gain the following benefits:
            You gain two tentacles that sprout from your body. As a bonus action, you can attempt to grapple 2 creatures within 15 feet of you. You can grapple a creature of one size bigger than you otherwise could by using both tentacles.
            As an action, you can squeeze creatures grappled by your tentacles. A grappled creature must make a Strength saving throw (against your spell save DC) or take 3d6 bludgeoning damage. You can rend to the damage of the squeezing tentacles, affecting all creatures grappled by them.
            You gain {{intelligence:modifier}} temporary hitpoints immediately and again at the start of each of your turns.</description>
            <description action="Action" usage="{{intelligence:modifier}}/Long Rest" level="10">As an action, you can reveal the anomaly. Tentacles erupt from your body, your eyes reveal the infinite void, and the might of the old gods fills you. The anomaly stays revealed for 1 minute. While the anomaly is revealed you gain the following benefits:
            You gain four tentacles that sprout from your body. As a bonus action, you can attempt to grapple 4 creatures within 30 feet of you. You can grapple a creature of one size bigger than you otherwise could by using two, and a creature of two sizes bigger than you could with four.
            As an action, you can squeeze creatures grappled by your tentacles. A grappled creature must make a Strength saving throw (against your spell save DC) or take 3d6 bludgeoning damage. You can rend to the damage of the squeezing tentacles, affecting all creatures grappled by them.
            You gain {{intelligence:modifier}} temporary hitpoints immediately and again at the start of each of your turns.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Awakened Mind" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_AWAKENED_MIND">
        <description>
            <p>Also at 3rd level, You can communicate telepathically with any creature you can see within 30 feet of you. You don't need to share a language with the creature for it to understand your telepathic utterances, but the creature must be able to understand at least one language. The creature doesn't gain telepathy itself, and can't respond in kind.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>You can communicate telepathically with any creature you can see within 30 feet of you. You don't need to share a language with the creature for it to understand your telepathic utterances, but the creature must be able to understand at least one language. The creature doesn't gain telepathy itself, and can't respond in kind.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Grasp of the Stars" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_GRASP_OF_THE_STARS">
        <description>
            <p>At 6th level, the damage of your tentacles counts as magical for the purposes of overcoming resistances and immunities. Additionally, you can throw any number of creatures grappled by your tentacles as an action a number of feet equal to your speed in a horizontal direction. A creature must make a Dexterity saving throw or land prone and take 3d6 bludgeoning damage, which you can rend to the damage for all thrown creatures. If you would throw it into another creature, it must also make a Dexterity saving throw or taking the same damage.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description action="Action">The damage of your tentacles counts as magical for the purposes of overcoming resistances and immunities. Additionally, you can throw any number of creatures grappled by your tentacles as an action {{speed}} feet in a horizontal direction. A creature must make a Dexterity saving throw or land prone and take 3d6 bludgeoning damage, which you can rend to the damage for all thrown creatures. If you would throw it into another creature, it must also make a Dexterity saving throw or taking the same damage.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="Greater Anomaly" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_GREATER_ANOMALY">
        <description>
            <p>Starting at 10th level, you can grapple creatures with your tentacles up to 30 feet away from you, and you can move creatures grappled by your tentacles up to 30 feet per turn, not including dragging them with you if you move.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>You can move creatures grappled by your tentacles up to 30 feet per turn, not including dragging them with you if you move.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

    <element name="To the Old Ones" type="Archetype Feature" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_ATAVIST_ANOMALOUS_TO_THE_OLD_ONES">
        <description>
            <p>Beginning at 18th level, you can devour the soul of a creature that dies while grappled by at least one of your tentacles. If you do so, for the duration of the current anomaly, you gain one additional tentacle, you can change your face into the creature's or back to your previous as an action, and you know everything that creature knew in life.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>You can devour the soul of a creature that dies while grappled by at least one of your tentacles. If you do so, for the duration of the current anomaly, you gain one additional tentacle, you can change your face into the creature's or back to your previous as an action, and you know everything that creature knew in life.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>
    
</elements>