<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
    <info>
        <name></name>
        <update version="0.0.1">
            <file name="source.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Zenoverlordian/swordmeow-atavist/main/source.xml" />
        </update>
    </info>
    
    <element name="SwordMeow Atavist" type="Source" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SOURCE_ATAVIST">
        <description>
            <![CDATA[<p>An armored frontlining human takes blow after blow, and when she begins to weaken, she becomes all the more savage - hitting harder, striking faster, dying slower. A wounded dog is lethal, but a wounded atavist is a bloody nightmare. With caution halfway around the world, she wounds her own arm, but the enemy falls to the ground as he takes all the pain. Another foe comes near, but finding her only stronger than she was previous.</p>
            <p>An orc throws more than his all into each blow, hurting himself in a magical effort to strengthen his blows, but knows it’s not enough. He stills and lets the alien forces take over his mind, as his body erupts aberrant flesh strips, covering him entirely, growing out of holes and hairs - eyes darkening and true horror creeping. If his mark doesn’t falter at the mere sight of the abomination, he will soon fall in battle.</p>
            <p>The fireball rounds the corners of the maze, the wizard’s foul fire chasing his would be killer down the hall, but a sacrificial slight crippling of his arm gives him the power he needs to dodge out of the fiery current.</p>
            <p>No matter their upbringing, race, culture, or even time period, atavists are united by their ability to make use of their own vitality in their weaponplay. There may have been bloodlines at one point, but those are gone now.</p>]]>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="abbreviation">Atavist</set>
            <set name="url">https://www.reddit.com/r/UnearthedArcana/comments/ckqnde/the_atavist_errata_the_blood_warriormage_class/</set>
            <set name="image">https://imgv2-2-f.scribdassets.com/img/document/370171069/original/8296b550a1/1615979025?v=1</set>
            <set name="author" abbreviation="SwordMeow" url="https://www.reddit.com/user/SwordMeow/submitted/">SwordMeow</set>
            <set name="official">false</set>
            <set name="supplement">false</set>
            <set name="playtest">false</set>
            <set name="third-party">false</set>
            <set name="homebrew">true</set>
            <set name="league">false</set>
            <set name="release">20200118</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
</elements>