<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
    
    <element name="Courageous Rebuttal" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_COURAGEOUS_REBUTTAL">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>As part of the reaction used to cast this spell, you use a weapon to make a melee weapon attack against the creature that attacked you, after the outcome of their attack is decided. If you hit, the target suffers the weapon’s normal damage, and you gain half the damage dealt in temporary hitpoints that last for up to 1 minute.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 reaction, which you take when a creature makes a melee attack against you</set>
            <set name="range">10 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a weapon</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Heart Sunder" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_HEART_SUNDER">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You cause a melee weapon you are holding to thirst for blood, opening a creature’s weaknesses. The first attack you make with that weapon on this turn adds 1d6 to the attack roll. On a hit, the target suffers the attack’s normal effects and the next weapon damage rolled against the target is automatically maximized.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Lesser Bloodsight" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_LESSER_BLOODSIGHT">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your eyes take on a crimson hue. For the duration, you can see the life force of nearby creatures within the spell’s range. When a creature is at full health, they appear perfectly normal, but as they become more wounded a red aura begins to surround them.</p>
            <p class="indent">You can notice when a creature’s current hitpoints are below their hitpoint maximum and half their hitpoint maximum. When a creature falls below their maximum, they glow red, and can be seen behind materials of 3 inches thick or less. Once a creature is below half of their maximum, you can see them even through walls.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Divination</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">true</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Withering Necrosis" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_WITHERING_NECROSIS">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You extend your hand and attempt to vastly decrease the health of a creature you grasp. Make a melee spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 5d6 necrotic damage at the start of its next turn.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the target takes an additional 1d6 damage for each spell slot above 1st.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Up to 1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Crourbat Call" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_CROURBAT_CALL">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>This spell creates an undead familiar. Organically created from the bites of vampires, cruorbats can be summoned for a short while through mirrored forms of hemomancy. When you cast this spell, choose a corpse of a Large or smaller bat within range. The target becomes a cruorbat, but only of a size fitting for its corpse (the statistics can be found on pg. 33 of the Dark Arts Player’s Companion).</p>
            <p class="indent">On each of your turns, you can verbally command the cruorbat you made if the cruorbat is within 60 feet of you. You decide what action it will take and where it will move during its next turn, or you can issue a general command, such as to guard a particular chamber or corridor.</p>
            <p class="indent">If you issue no commands, the cruorbat only defends itself against hostile creatures. Once given an order, the cruorbat continues to follow it until its task is complete.</p>
            <p class="indent">The creature is under your control for 24 hours, after which it stops obeying any commands you’ve given it. To maintain control of the creautre for another 24 hours, you must cast this spell on the cruorbat again before the current 24-hour period ends. This use of this spell reasserts your control of the cruorbat you animated with this spell, rather than animating a new one.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 minute</set>
            <set name="range">10 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">some fruit</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Needle and Thread" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_NEEDLE_AND_THREAD">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Select a target with blood within range, who must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failure, it takes 3d8 piercing damage and its blood explodes in three sharpened needles from its body to as many creatures or objects of your choice as there are needles, each target of which must be within 30 feet of the original. A secondary target must make the same save, taking 1d8 piercing damage per needle on a failure, or none on a success. If the first target succeeds on the saving throw, the first target only takes half as much piercing damage.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the first target takes 1d8 additional damage and releases one more needle for each spell slot above 2nd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">150 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a needle and thread</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Polyphemus' Might" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_POLYPHEMUS_MIGHT">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You imbue one creature of your choice within range a shadow of giant’s might. The target gains a number of d4s equal to your level in temporary hitpoints, and while those hitpoints last, they have advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened, and roll damage dice twice for melee attacks, choosing the higher result.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Enchantment</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a giant eye</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Coalesce Humours" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_COALESCE_HUMOURS">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Choose a corpse with blood or a large volume of blood within range. You extract the blood, which comes to life, so that it becomes a blood ooze under your control for the duration of the spell.</p>
            <p class="indent">The coalesced creature is friendly to you and your companions. It acts on your initiative and has its own actions. It obeys any verbal commands you issue to it. If you don’t issue any commands, the blood ooze defends itself from hostile creatures, but otherwise takes no actions.</p>
            <p class="indent">If your concentration is broken, the ooze doesn’t disappear. Instead, you lose control of the blood ooze, it becomes hostile towards all non-ooze creatures, and might attack. An uncontrolled blood ooze can’t be dismissed by you and it disappears 8 hours after you coalesced it.</p>
            <p class="indent">If it drops to 0 hitpoints, it loses life and splashes into a pool of blood that can be coalesced once more for this spell. The statistics can be found on pg. 44 of the Dark Arts Player’s Companion.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 minute</set>
            <set name="range">90 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 8 hours</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Redwood Expansion" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_REDWOOD_EXPANSION">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>For the duration, you cause a creature of your choice to undergo a spontaneous expansion of sinews, bones, muscle, organs; their entire body. If the target is unwilling, it can make a Constitution throw to be unaffected on a success. Everything the creature is wearing and carrying changes size with it. Any item dropped by an affected creature returns to normal size at once.</p>
            <p class="indent">The target’s size quadruples in all dimensions and its weight is multiplied by thirty-two. This growth increases its size by two categories—from Medium to Huge, for example. If there isn’t enough room for the target to double its size, the creature attains the maximum possible size in the space available. Until the spell ends, the target also has advantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws, and can reroll one of the dice once. The target’s weapons also grow to match its new size. While these weapons are enlarged, the target’s attacks with them add your spellcasting modifier as extra damage.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Aura of Decay" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_AURA_OF_DECAY">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A diseased aura radiates from you within range. Until the spell ends, the aura moves with you, centered on you. Each hostile creature that enters the area for the first time on a turn or starts its turn within it has disadvantage on death saving throws and must make a Constitution saving throw or take 5d6 necrotic damage.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the spell’s radius increases by 15 feet for each spell slot above 4th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (30-foot radius)</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Quicken Atavism" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_QUICKEN_ATAVISM">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You perform a rite of blood on a young person. Choose a humanoid that is a number of years old or less equal to your spellcasting modifier. You imbue them with an atavistic spark, granting them a chance at developing atavism, which takes a full month to mature. Roll percentile dice. On a result of your level or lower, the child’s Constitution score raises to 15 if it were lower and they become a 1st-level atavist after the maturation time.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the humanoid’s maximum age increases by 5 years and the casting time halves for each spell slot above 4th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">16 hours</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Eternal</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">true</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Exoscleroma" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_EXOSCLEROMA">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You touch a creature who must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failure, they are cursed, and their bones slowly begin to dissolve and regrow under their skin. This spell has no effect against creatures who are immune to poison damage or the poisoned condition. After they finish their first long rest, they become poisoned. After the second, deafened; after the third, restrained; fourth, incapacitated; fifth, paralyzed; sixth, petrified.</p>
            <p class="indent">To be cured a creature must be healed by a healing spell or any restoration spell of the same level of day progression they are on or higher. Once three days have passed for a petrified creature under the effect of the spell, only 9th level magic can cure them.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Exsangruinate" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_EXSANGUINATE">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Choose a creature within range that has blood. They must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failure, half of their blood falls through their skin to the ground in a puddle of difficult terrain in a 10-foot-radius around them, they take 10d10 necrotic damage, and they become incapacitated until the end of their next turn.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Up to 1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Haemorrhaging Rupture" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_HAEMORRHAGING_RUPTURE">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You momentarily rip apart blood vessels of a creature you choose within range, who must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failure, for every 5 feet of movement they make for the duration to a maximum of 60, they lose 2d12 hitpoints due to blood loss or half as much on a success as their blood pours through their skin and out of their body, as if they were a cup overflowing with water. They take this damage even if they were moved against their will. At the end of each of its turns, the target can make another Constitution saving throw. For any success, the spell ends.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Enchantment</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Eternal Blood" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_ETERNAL_BLOOD">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You touch a creature and grant it a momentary dominion over death. If a creature dies while under the effect of this spell, they are revived after 1 minute from their remains, or, if none remain, their place of death.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 minute</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">8 hours</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Greater Withering" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_GREATER_WITHERING">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A creature you touch must make a Constitution saving throw or be afflicted with a living greater withering curse. On a failed save, immediately and at the end of each long rest that they take, they lose 1 point from their Strength and Constitution scores. If either fall below 4, they can’t move, and if either fall below 1, they die.</p>
            <p class="indent">This curse can only be removed by a spell of 7th level or higher, such as a 7th level remove curse or regenerate.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Necromancy</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Marrowmelt" type="Spell" source="SwordMeow Atavist" id="ID_SWORDMEOW_ATAVIST_SPELL_MARROWMELT">
        <supports>Atavist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You snap your fingers and attempt to cause the spine of a creature with one within range to break in half and then melt into marrow. The target chosen must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failure, they are permanently paralyzed.</p>
            <p class="indent">This paralysis can only be cured by a regenerate spell of 9th level.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">90 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
</elements>